Finding Aid for Michigan Peaceworks records, 2001-2011
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Michigan Peaceworks records
2001-2011
Michigan Peaceworks.
2010096 Bj 2
Michigan Peaceworks (MPW) was an Ann Arbor based grassroots organization dedicated to peace, social justice, and human rights that was founded in 2001 following the September 11th attacks. The collection includes material related to their public events and outreach activities in Ann Arbor. These events and activities are well represented in posters, fliers, and photographs.
4.5 linear feet in 6 boxes
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was the gift of the organization (donor no. 10344 ) and came to the library in 2010-2011.
No further additions to the records are expected.
The record group is open to research.
Michigan Peaceworks (MPW) was an Ann Arbor based grassroots organization dedicated to peace, social justice, and human rights. It was founded in 2001 following the September 11th attacks as the Ann Arbor Area Committee for Peace, which later transitioned into Michigan Peaceworks. The organization closed at the end of 2011 due to a lack of funding and a decrease in volunteers.
During its 10 years of operation, Michigan Peaceworks principally hosted rallies, marches, and vigils protesting the wars in Iraq and Afghanistan. They were also heavily involved in the training of youth activists and the Rabih Haddad due process case.
The Michigan Peaceworks Collection (4.5 linear feet) is largely composed of visual material in the form of photographs, flyers, and posters, related to events and rallies sponsored by Michigan Peaceworks and offers strong documentation of the peace community in Michigan in the decade following the September 11th attacks. The collection has been arranged in the following series: Administrative Files, Events and Activities, Publications and Outreach, Topical Files, Digital Material, and Visual Material.
Subjects:
Ann Arbor (Mich.); Iraq War, 2003--Protest movements--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Peace--Societies, etc.; Michigan Peaceworks.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Demonstrations--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Iraq War, 2003--Protest movements--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Protest movements--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Michigan Peaceworks.
Genre Terms:
CD-ROMs.; DVDs.; Photographs.; Posters.
- Administrative Files
  The Administrative Files (1.2 linear feet) contain material related to the formation of the Ann Arbor Committee for Peace, material from Board of Directors meetings, and chronological files documenting Michigan Peacework's activities through press clippings and fliers.
  - Album (Box 1)
  - A Moveable Peace Funding Prospectus, 2011 (Box 1)
  - Ann Arbor Area Committee for Peace
    - Final Report (Box 1)
    - General (Box 1)
    - Strategic Committee Meeting, 2002 (Box 1)
    - Strategy, 2003 (Box 1)
    - Structure Meeting, 2002 (Box 1)
  - Board of Directors
    - Agendas, Minutes, and Reports, 2006 (Box 1)
    - Agendas, Meetings, and Minutes, 2007-2011; 3 folders (Box 1)
    - Meeting notes and agendas, 2005-2006 (Box 1)
    - Meetings, 2010 (Box 1)
    - Meeting Agendas, 2005-2006 (Box 1)
    - Member Materials, 2007 (Box 1)
    - Member Materials, 2009 (Box 1)
    - Members Binder, 2003-2011 (Box 1)
    - Organizational and Business Documents, 2003-2008 (Box 1)
    - Retreat, 2010 (Box 1)
  - Chronological Files, 2001-2006; 6 folders (Box 1)
  - Elected Official Correspondence, 2002-2004 (Box 1)
  - Executive Director Transition (Box 1)
  - Fundraising Committee, 2006 (Box 1)
  - History (Box 1)
  - Liberty Bell Award, 2009 (Box 1)
  - Logos (Box 1)
  - March and Rally Planning (Box 1)
  - Media Consultancy, 2003 (Box 1)
  - Michigan Peace Network -- General, 2007 (Box 1)
  - Michigan Peace Network Meeting, 2006 (Box 1)
  - Middle East statement, 2004 (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 1)
  - Student Activism Survey, 2006 (Box 1)
  - Summer Activist Training, 2008 (Box 1)
  - Staff reports, 2003-2008 (Box 2)
  - Task lists, 2006 (Box 2)
- Events and Activities
  The Events and Activities (0.6 linear feet) series contains fliers, programs, and correspondence related to events sponsored by Michigan Peaceworks. These events include marches, rallies, candlelight vigils, film screenings, and fundraisers.
  - 4th of July Parade, 2002-2006 (Box 2)
  - Brewing Peace, 2004-2007 (Box 2)
  - Candlelight Vigils
    - 9/11 Vigils, 2002-2003 (Box 2)
    - No More War Victims -- Candlelight Vigil for Peace, 2003 (Box 2)
    - 1,000 Deaths in Iraq, 2004 (Box 2)
    - 2,000 Deaths in Iraq, 2005 (Box 2)
    - Candlelight Vigil for Peace and a Ceasefire in the Middle East, 2006 (Box 2)
  - Day of War Demonstration, 2003 (Box 2)
  - Dingell Roundtable, 2003 (Box 2)
  - Fahrenheit 9/11 screening, 2004 (Box 2)
  - Five Year Birthday Party, 2006 (Box 2)
  - Get Out the Vote (GOTV), 2004 (Box 2)
  - Halloween Party, 2003 (Box 2)
  - Hotel Rwanda screening, 2005 (Box 2)
  - In My Country screening, 2005 (Box 2)
  - Iraq Exit Roundtable, 2005 (Box 2)
  - Iraq: Soldiers Saying No to War, 2006 (Box 2)
  - Iraq Water Project, 2009 (Box 2)
  - Living for 32 screening, 2007 (Box 2)
  - Marches
    - National Day of Action, 2002 (Box 2)
    - Peace Parade, 2003 (Box 2)
    - Peace, March, 2005 (Box 2)
    - Funeral, March, 2008 (Box 2)
  - Merton Center, 2006 (Box 2)
  - Organizing for Change Conference (Box 2)
  - Peace Cafes (Box 2)
  - Presidential Debate Forum, 2004 (Box 2)
  - September 11th Families Event, 2002 (Box 2)
  - Sheehan Rally, 2005 (Box 2)
  - SOUP -- State of the Union, 2006 (Box 2)
  - Spy-In, 2006 (Box 2)
  - Stop the War Day of Action, 2005 (Box 2)
  - Stop the War Rally, 2006 (Box 2)
  - "The Real About Race" (Box 2)
  - True State of the Union, 2004 (Box 2)
  - The World Still Says No to War, 2004 (Box 2)
  - War Rally, 2010 (Box 2)
  - "Working for Peace and Social Justice in Michigan", 2010 (Box 2)
  - Youth Outreach Training, 2006 (Box 2)
  - Youth Peace Summit, 2007 (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous Events
    - Event Flyers, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Event Programs (Box 2)
- Publications and Outreach
  The Publications and Outreach (0.7 linear feet) series contains copies of publications produced by Michigan Peaceworks, including ads placed in newspapers, letters to the editor, press releases, topical fliers, and the Armistice zine. This series also includes material related to outreach activities, including podcasts and speaking engagements.
  - Ad, February 2, 2003 (Box 2)
  - Armistice Zine, 2007 (Box 2)
  - Big Lie Campaign, 2003 (Box 2)
  - Bumper stickers (Box 3)
  - Buttons, 2011 (Box 3)
  - Flyers (Box 3)
  - Fundraising solicitations, 2006 (Box 3)
  - Immigration (Box 3)
  - Letters to the Editor, 2001-2005 (Box 3)
  - Member mail, 2002 (Box 3)
  - Misleader ad, 2003 (Box 3)
  - Peace card and Peace ad, 2001 (Box 3)
  - Peace post cards (Box 3)
  - Podcasts, 2006 (Box 3)
  - Post 9/11 Mailing, 2002 (Box 3)
  - Press Conference, 2003 (Box 3)
  - Press Pack (Box 3)
  - Press Releases (Box 3)
  - Safety op-ed, 2005 (Box 3)
  - Signature Ads
    - Signature Ad Plans (Box 3)
    - Signature Ad, 2002 (Box 3)
    - Iraq, 2004 (Box 3)
    - July 4th Ad, 2004-2004 (Box 3)
  - Talks and Presentations, 2003-2006 (Box 3)
  - Tuesday Working Group, 2009 (Box 3)
  - Veterans for Peace Press Packet, 2004 (Box 3)
  - Yard Signs, 2004-2005 (Box 3)
- Topical Files
  The Topical Files (0.8 linear feet) are principally composed of press clippings and correspondence related to subjects of interest to Michigan Peaceworks. The material related to the Rabih Haddad case is especially thorough. This series also includes a file of general press clippings maintained by the organization.
  - Afghanistan, 2001-2002 (Box 3)
  - A. J. Muste Memorial Institute Essay Series: Martin Luther King, Jr. (Box 3)
  - Amnesty International Report, 2003 (Box 3)
  - Bring the Troops Home Campaign Toolkit (Box 3)
  - Department of Justice Interview, 2001 (Box 3)
  - Guantanamo, 2005-2006 (Box 3)
  - Gun Violence, 2011 (Box 3)
  - Hate mail, 2002-2008 (Box 3)
  - Hellopeace,org, 2006 (Box 3)
  - Impeachment, 2005-2006 (Box 3)
  - Iraq War, 2010 (Box 3)
  - Military Families Speak Out, 2003 (Box 3)
  - Needmor Fund, 2005 (Box 3)
  - Non-Violent Dialogue (Box 3)
  - Palestine (Box 3)
  - Peace movement, 2001-2003 (Box 3)
  - Peru, 1989-2011 (Box 3)
  - Press clippings
    - Ad-Hoc Activities, 2001-2003 (Box 3)
    - General, 2 folders (Box 3)
    - M20 Media, 2002-2004 (Box 4)
  - Rabih Haddad Case, 2002 (Box 4)
  - Religious Freedom, 2010 (Box 4)
  - School of the Americas, 2010 (Box 4)
  - Senior Advocacy, 2007 (Box 4)
  - Sweat Free Michigan, 2006-2008 (Box 4)
  - Torture, 2004-2005 (Box 4)
  - Voting machines, 2003 (Box 4)
  - Youth activism, 2004-2006 (Box 4)
- Digital Material
  The Digital Materials (0.3 linear feet) includes DVDs and digital photographs documenting a variety of events sponsored by Michigan Peaceworks.
  - DVDs
    - 5th Annual Iraq War March Video (Box 4)
    - Ann Arbor Winter Soldier Event, 2008 (Box 4)
    - Concert for Peace, 2008; 3 optical disks DVDs (Box 4)
    - Extraordinary Rendition, 2009 (Box 4)
    - PeaceJam Overview and Interview with Shirin Ebadi (Box 4)
    - Rageism, 2008; 2 optical disks DVDs (Box 4)
    - Voices of Youth Peace DVD, 2005; 2 optical disks DVDs (Box 4)
  - CD-Rs
    - 4th of July Parade photographs, 2005; 2 optical disks CD-Rs (Box 4)
    - Ann Arbor Musicians for Peace, 2004; 2 optical disks CD-Rs (Box 4)
    - Arlington Midwest, 2004; 1 optical disks CD-Rs (Box 4)
    - Chicago Media, October 27, 2007; 1 optical disks CD-Rs (Box 4)
    - Cindy Sheehan Support Rally Photographs, 2005; 1 optical disks CD-Rs (Box 4)
    - Gregory Fox Photography, 2004 (Box 4)
    - Michigan Peaceworks July 4th, March, 2006; 1 optical disks CD-Rs (Box 4)
    - MPW photographs, 2004-2010; 1 optical disks CD-Rs (Box 4)
    - Peace March photographs, 2005; 2 optical disks CD-Rs (Box 4)
    - Peace Rally photographs, 2004; 1 optical disks CD-Rs (Box 4)
    - Peace Vigil Photographs, 2007; 1 optical disks CD-Rs (Box 4)
    - Stop the War March photographs and "Turn Yourself In" mugshots, 2006; 1 optical disks CD-Rs (Box 4)
- Visual Materials
  The Visual Materials (0.3) includes photographs of Michigan Peaceworks events and material displayed in the organization's headquarters. Included are informational banners used in marches and displays. One is a timeline of Peaceworks activities.
  - Photographs
    - Halloween (Box 4)
    - Rabih Haddad vigils (Box 4)
    - Worlds Largest Peace Sign (Box 4)
    - Miscellaneous photographs, 2 folders (Box 4)
  - Display Material
    - Archived decor (Box 4)
    - Display Boards (Box 4)
    - Photograph Boards
      - Bulletin Boards, prior to removal of photographs (CD-R) (Box 4)
      - Candlelight Vigil for Remembrance and Peace, 2002 (Box 4)
      - MPW Float, July 4, 2006 (Box 4)
      - Youth Peace Night, May 5, 2006 (Box 4)
      - Unlabelled panel, 2 folders (Box 4)
      - Jobs Not War in 4, July 2004; 2004 (Box 4)
      - Unlabelled panel (Box 4)
      - The World Still Say No to War, March 20, 2004 (Box 4)
      - The Cradle of Civilization, does not include photographs (Box 4)
  - Display Material
    - Armistice Zine (Box 5)
    - Iraq Water Project (Box 5)
    - Publicity Album (Box 5)
    - Signs, Posters, and Oversized Newspaper Clippings (Box 5)
    - Rolled informational banners and timeline of organization's activities, 10 rolls (Box 6)